玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
我们的太阳是否存在一颗复仇星
Does our Sun have a deadly nemesis...
让地球生命在劫难逃呢？
that dooms life on our planet?
有可能穿越时间旅行呢？
ls it possible to travel through time?
这是最大的问题之一
lt is one of the greatest questions.
物质的邪恶孪生兄弟究竟是怎么一回事？
What happened to matter's evil twin?
脑子里需要有个说法
The mind hunts for an explanation.
火星上的水怎么会消失的？
How did the water on Mars disappear?
大爆炸之前是怎么回事？
And what came before the Big Bang?
这就是科学上最大的谜团
This is the greatest mystery in all of science.
大问题 又是边缘科学
Big questions, and cutting-edge science.
宇宙之未解之谜
"The Universe: Unexplained Mysteries."
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第十一集 未解之谜
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 11of19 Unexplained.Mysteries
在宇宙未解之谜里
Among the unexplained mysteries in the universe...
有一个对生活在地球上的我们尤为紧迫
one has a particular urgency...for those of us who enjoy living on planet Earth.
地球人真的难以摆脱每隔2600万年一次的灭绝吗？
Do Earthlings have...a regularly scheduled date with extinction...once every 26 million years?
要是这样那么究竟是什么引发
And if so, what causes...
这个周期性的毁灭的豪雨的呢？
this periodic hard rain of destruction?
你会看到这个大爆炸
You have this enormous explosion.
数千英里之内的东西统统被消灭
Anything within thousands of miles will be killed.
你会看到首先是海啸的冲击波
You're talking here...first of the blast wave of the tsunami.
会看到高温
You're talking about the enormous heat.
大火吞噬了地球
Fires all around the globe...
然后一片昏暗
and then darkness.
数百万年以来
For millions 0f years...
太空中的大量物体撞击地球
enormous objects from space have slammed into Earth...
带来了灾难
with disastrous results.
尤卡坦半岛水域遭遇的撞击
One impact in the waters off the Yucatan Peninsula...
是6500年前恐龙灭绝的罪魁祸首
is blamed for the extinction of the dinosaurs...65 million years ago.
然而这不是地球上第一次大消亡
But this wasn't the first mass extinction on Earth...
也不会是最后一次
and it probably won't be the last.
它不是史上最大的灭绝事件
And it wasn't the biggest mass extinction event of all time...
因为在二叠纪大绝灭事件中
because that one was the Permean Extinction...
有95%的海洋物种和80%的陆地物种惨遭不测
in which 95 percent...of the species in the oceans died...and about 80 percent 0f those on land.
所以曾经发生过剧烈的灭绝事件
So radical extinction events have happened.
有些科学家认为
Some scientists believe...
这些消亡 灭绝事件曾定期发生过
these periods of death and destruction...happen like clockwork.
有些古生物学家发现了奇怪的模式
Some paleontologists found a very strange pattern.
他们发现诸如灭绝恐龙那样的大灭绝
What they found were the great extinctions...such as ones that killed the dinosaurs...
当然 还有其它并非随机发生的
but others, too, didn't happen at random times...
而似乎是按时间表的安排发生的
but seemed to occur on a regular time schedule.
非常奇怪
That was very strange.
每2600万年就会发生灭绝事件
They were disappearing every 26 million years.
需要讨个说法
lt was begging for an explanation.
天体物理学家理查德·穆勒认为
Astrophysicist Richard Muller believes...
这种周期性灭绝的解释
the explanation for this periodic destruction...
就是有一颗昏暗的红矮星
is a dim red dwarf star...
潜伏在太阳系的边缘
lurking on the edge of the solar system...
他恰如其分地将它称之为 复仇星
a star that he fittingly calls Nemesis.
根据他的理论
According to his theory...
复仇星是我们太阳尚未发现的伴星
Nemesis is an undiscovered companion star to our own Sun.
它以长椭圆轨道穿行于
lt travels between one and three light-years...
距离太阳系中心1到3光年之间
from the center of the solar system...on an elongated elliptical orbit.
在复仇星每2600万年最靠近太阳时
As Nemesis makes its closest approach to the Sun...every 26 million years...
其轨道正好穿过奥尔特云
its orbit takes it right through the Oort Cloud...
那里聚集着上万亿的彗星
a collection of an estimated trillion comets...
围绕着太阳系
surrounding our solar system.
到了那时 太阳系的秩序
That's when the order of the solar system...
会变得特别混乱
turns especially chaotic.
此时 就会发生复仇星靠近彗星
When that happens...Nemesis gets close to the comets...
扰乱它们的轨道
and perturbs their orbit.
根据穆勒的理论 引力破坏的原因在于
According to Muller's theory, the gravitational disruption...
这颗无伤大雅的小恒星
caused by this small innocuous star...
造成了长期安分守己的彗星
causes long-undisturbed comets...
挣脱了它们在奥尔特云里的轨道
to break away from their orbits in the Oort Cloud.
在太阳引力的牵引下
Pulled towards the Sun by its gravity...
十亿彗星冲入太阳系
a billion comets are sent careening...toward the inner solar system.
少数免不了和地球不期相遇
A handful inevitably cross paths with the Earth...
导致大碰撞 大灭绝
resulting in massive impacts and mass extinctions.
主张我们的太阳
The claim that our Sun...
有一个未被发现的伴侣 死亡之星
has an undiscovered companion death star...
是有争议的
is controversial.
多数科学家认为太阳
Most scientists believe that the Sun...
是没伴的孤单恒星
is a solitary star with no companions.
然而 在宇宙间
But in the universe...
双星 甚至三星通过引力组合在一起
binary or even triplet stars grouped together by gravity...
比比皆是
are the norm.
我们银河系里大部分恒星
The majority of stars in our galaxy...
都属于双星或三星
are parts of either binary or triple stars...
因此 太阳不出意料可能是双星的一员的想法
and so the idea that the Sun...conceivably could be part of a binary...
从各方面来看都不为过
isn't crazy from that point ofview at all.
这是个有趣的问题
lt's an interesting question.
即使 太阳可能存在一个孪生同伴
Even if the Sun could conceivably have...a binary companion...
天文学家也从未见到过有这样的双星系
astronomers have never observed a binary system...
两颗恒星会分得像
in which the pair of stars are as far apart...
穆勒所说的太阳与复仇星那么遥远
as Muller claims our Sun and Nemesis would be.
穆勒需要证明复仇星真的存在
Muller needed proof that Nemesis was real.
1997年 航天局的一项使命
ln 1997, a Nasa mission began...
有可能揭开这谜团
that had the potential to shed light on the mystery.
两微米全天监测计划 (2MASS)
The Two Micron All-Sky Survey, or 2MASS...
利用两台红外望远镜
used twin infrared telescopes...
来寻找宇宙间先前未曾发现的恒星
to scour the universe for previously unknown stars.
2MASS擅长发现银河系内外难以发现的天体
2MASS specialized in hard-to-find bodies...in and near our galaxy...
到眼下已经获得了200多万张图像
and to date, has produced over two million images.
如果复仇星存在 2MASS应该会发现的
lf Nemesis was out there, 2MASS should have spotted it.
然而 观察并未发现任何东西
But the survey never detected anything...
符合穆勒所描述的死亡之星
fitting the description of Muller's death star.
我们观测过
We've looked.
我们致力于寻找死亡之星 复仇星
We've looked real hard for death star, for Nemesis...
然而我们一无所获
and we can't find it anywhere.
穆勒对2MASS未发现复仇星并不感到惊讶
But Muller isn't surprised 2MASS didn't find his Nemesis.
原因是在1光年左右的地方
The reason is at the distance of about one light-year...
也就是 它获得2600万年的轨道该处的位置上
which is the distance it would have...in order to have a 26-million-year orbit...
它移动缓慢
its motion is very little...
所以 它应该不会错过搜索邻近恒星的标准观察
and so it would've been missed by the standard surveys...that look for nearby stars.
另一种可能就是 复仇星有可能是颗褐矮星
Another possibility is that Nemesis may actually be...a brown dwarf.
这种衰落的恒星
These failed stars...
比红矮星小多了
are much smaller than red dwarfs...
具有长椭圆轨道
and with a highly elliptical orbit...
多数时间 褐矮星远离地球
a brown dwarfwould remain far from Earth most of the time...
天文学家很难观察到
and out of the watchful eye of astronomers.
如果情况属实
lf that's the case...
复仇星就有可能轻易逃脱2MASS的雷达
Nemesis could have easily slipped under the 2MASS radar.
穆勒誓言继续搜寻
Richard Muller vows to continue looking...
计划了另一个更加详细的研究
and plans yet another more detailed study.
他找到复仇星只是个时间的问题
He believes it's only a matter of time...before Nemesis is found.
有很多星存在
There are lots of stars out there.
有数百万个
There are millions of them.
然而 在大海里捞针时
But when you find the needle in a haystack...
你找到它 叫道 啊 就是它
you could look at it and say, "Well, that's not hay."
这也一样
Similarly with this.
一旦我们找到复仇星 会计算其轨道
When we find Nemesis, we'll measure the orbit...
会证明它就是复仇星
and we'll prove that it's Nemesis.
在我们宇宙所有未解之谜中
Of all the unexplained mysteries in our universe...
或许最有趣和最具争议性的
perhaps the most tantalizing and controversial...
就是能否穿越时间
is whether it's possible to travel through time.
我们真的能够回到过去吗？
Can we really travel back in the past?
我们真的能改变自己的命运吗？
Can we really alter our destiny?
这是最大的问题之一
lt was one of the greatest questions.
1955年 罗恩·马利特才10岁时
ln 1955, Ron Mallett was only10 years old...
他父亲死于心脏病
when his father died of a heart attack.
哀痛不已 少年马利特渴望
Grief-stricken, young Mallett yearned...
能够有种方法让他重见父亲
for a way he could see his father again...
以挽救其生命
and perhaps save his life.
他去世一年后
About a year after he died...
我读到了H.G.韦尔斯的书《时间机器》
l came across H.G. Wells' book, "The Time Machine"...
就是它拯救了我
and that is what saved me...
因为 我想 如果我能想韦尔斯说的那样
because l thought if l could build a time machine...
打造一架时间机器的话
as H.G. Wells talked about...
我就能够回到过去
then l could go back into the past...
设法挽救其生命 并重新看到他
and try to save his life and see him again.
因此 我沉湎于设法打造时间机器的想法之中
And so l become obsessed with the notion...of trying to build a time machine.
先生们 我说的是穿越时间
Gentlemen, l am talking about traveling through time.
《时间机器》是本科幻作品
"The Time Machine" was a work offiction...
但是马利特很快发现穿越时间的神秘概念
but Mallett soon discovered there was science...
有科学支撑
to support the mysterious notion 0f time travel...
出典正是来自爱因斯坦
and the source was none other than Albert Einstein.
爱因斯坦推断时空是关联的
Einstein theorized that space and time were linked...
因此 人们可以将时空想象成织物或床单
so that one could imagine space-time...as a sort offabric or sheet.
在他的广义相对论里
With his general theory of relativity...
爱因斯坦表明大物体
Einstein showed that a massive object...
如行星 恒星或黑洞之类
like a planet, a star, or a black hole...
实际上弯曲了时空的结构
actually warps the fabric of space and time.
事实上 爱因斯坦认为引力
ln fact, Einstein believed that gravity...
将我们束缚在地球上
the force that binds us to the Earth...
以及维系地球围绕太阳这样的力
and keeps the Earth in orbit around the Sun...
实际上就是这种弯曲的结果
is reallyjust an effect of this warping.
对于马利特来说这种思想 宇宙弯曲的概念
For Mallett, this mind- and universe-bending idea...
具有深刻的内涵
has far-reaching implications...
因为 你如果能创造出足够的引力
because if you could generate enough gravity...
把时间弯曲成环状
to twist time into a loop...
那么你或许就能创造出一个通道
perhaps you could create a pathway...
往后或往前穿越时间
for moving backwards and forwards through time.
爱因斯坦的理论激发了马利特探求
Einstein's theories fueled Ron Mallett's quest...
如何去打造自己的时间机器
to learn how to build his own time machine.
然而 穿越时间并不是一个
But time travel wasn't a subject...
可以让严谨的科学家在户外研究的课题
that could be studied by serious scientists...out in the open.
其实
As a matter offact...
我利用了一个封面故事来为我服务
l used a cover story that worked for me.
我研究黑洞
l studied black holes...
因为黑洞让我明白了
because black holes allowed me to understand...
爱因斯坦的理论是如何影响时空的
how Einstein's theory affected time and every...
那是个荒唐的想法 但却被认为是合理的荒唐
it was a crazy idea, but it was considered legitimate crazy.
因此 我从事的这项研究
So l built my career on studying that...
能够用上爱因斯坦的广义相对论
and being able to use...Einstein's General Theory of Relativity.
黑洞 塌缩恒星的巨大残骸
Black holes, the massive remnants of collapsed stars...
拥有几乎无可匹敌的引力
have an almost unmatched gravitational power...
来扭曲时空
to distort space and time...
那就是马利特要的
which is exactly what Mallett wanted to do.
但是 他又如何在实验室里创造出
But how could he create in the laboratory...
能弯曲时空的有足够物质的致密的东西呢？
something jam-packed with enough matter...to actually warp space-time?
为了得到灵感 马利特再次求助于爱因斯坦
For inspiration, Mallett turned again to Einstein...
以及他著名的方程式 E=MC？
and his most famous equation, E equals MC squared...
它表明了物质与能量只是同一种东西的不同形式
which showed that matter and energy...are just different forms of the same thing.
所以按照爱因斯坦的理论
So following Einstein's theory...
光就是能够弯曲时空的能量
light, which is energy...should be able to warp space and time...
如同大物体那样
just like a massive object does.
我们过去的概念
We're used to the notion...
引力是物质创造的
that gravity is created by matter.
但是在爱因斯坦的理论里
But it turns out that in Einstein's theory...
光可以创造出引力
light can create gravity...
这就是我研究的依据
and that is what my work is based on.
换句话说 如果引力能够影响时间
ln otherwords, if gravity can affect time...
光可以产生引力
and light can create gravity...
那么光也可以影响时间
then light can affect time.
马利特建了一个模型来论证自己的想法
Mallett has built a model to demonstrate his concept...
即循环的激光束可以创造出时光隧道
that a circulating laser beam can create a tunnel of light...
来扭曲时空
that twists space and time.
它有四束交叉的激光束
lt has four intersecting laser beams.
在光柱里的那个区域里
The region within that column of light...
将会表现出空间正被扭曲
would represent the region in which space is being twisted.
最终
And eventually...
时间也会被光柱所扭曲
time would also get twisted by this column of light.
这就能够让我们回到过去
And this would allow us to travel back into the past.
首个时间旅行者
The first time traveler...
肯定是比人类小得多的东西
will have to be something much smaller than a human being...
中子之类的次原子微粒
a subatomic particle like a neutron.
我们努力研究的不是人类
What we're trying to do is not human beings...
而是设法将次原子微粒信息传过去
but to try to send subatomic particles...information at that.
其本身就是个巨大的飞跃
And that is a huge leap in itself...
因为想象一下
because imagine...
如果我们能够将信息传回过去
ifwe can send information back into the past...
告诉我们未来的灾难
that could tell us about future disasters...
那就能够预防那些灾难了
and be able to avert those disasters.
我们可以通过这杯咖啡的简单比喻
We can understand...how circulating a light beam can twist space and time...
来了解循环光束是如何扭曲时空的
by simple analogy with a cup of coffee.
我们把咖啡和杯子看作是空间
We think of the coffee and the cup...as being like empty space...
而将小勺看作是循环光束
and we think of the spoon...as being like a circulating light beam.
你可以看到我搅动时咖啡的情况
You can see what happens to the coffee as l stir it.
咖啡在打转
The coffee swirls around.
那就是循环光束在空间里的动作
Well, that's what the circulating light beam...is doing to empty space.
我们能够在咖啡放进咖啡豆的例子中看到这种影响
And we could see the effect 0f this...in the case of the coffee by putting in a coffee bean.
随着我的搅动
As l swirl it around...
咖啡豆跟着转动起来
the coffee bean gets swirled around.
对于激光 由于光束在循环
ln the case of the laser, as the beam is circulating...
我们就放入中子这样的次原子粒子
we put a subatomic particle called a neutron in.
随着我们搅动空间
And as we stir the space around...
中子也跟着转动起来
the neutron will get swirled around...
就像咖啡豆一样
just like the coffee bean.
好 请记住 在爱因斯坦的理论中
Now, remember, in Einstein's theory...
空间和时间是结合在一起的
space and time are connected...
因此 空间的搅动也会造成
so that swirling of space will cause...
直线的时间被搅动成环状
the straight line of time to be swirled into a loop.
沿着那个时间环 我们可以从过去
And along that loop in time we can go from the past...
走到现在 走到未来
to the present, to the future...
然后再返回过去
and then back into the past.
科幻小说将时间机器米描述成
Science fiction has depicted time machines...
允许在时间里任意来回
as allowing unrestrained travel forward and backwards in time.
然而 马利特警告称 时间旅行者
But Mallett cautions that a time traveler...
只能够往回旅行到
could onlyjourney back as far as the moment...
时间机器最早打开的那一刻
that the time machine was first turned on.
也就是说 如果我今天打开这机器
ln otherwords, if l turned the device on today...
然后在100年里把它一直开着
and l leave it on for a hundred years...
那么 百年后的某个人
then someone a hundred years from now...
就能够往回75年 50年 25年
could travel back 75 years, 50 years, 25 years...
一路回到我打开机器的这一刻
all the way back to the moment l turned the device on.
但是 他们无法再往前了
But they can't travel earlier than that...
因为 机器在更早些并不存在
because the device didn't exist earlier than that...
这就是机器所产生的结果
and it's the device that's creating the effect...
所以 对他们的时间穿梭具体进入哪里没有什么关系
so there's nothing for them to time-travel...to materialize into.
这种限制意味着马利特的时间机器
This limitation means that Mallett's time machine...
绝不可能给他有能力
could never give him the capability...
回到1955年挽救其父亲生命的能力
to travel back to 1955 to save his father's life.
为此 还需要某些我们这个世界以外的科技
To do that would take some technology...from out of this world.
理论上
Theoretically...
发达的外星文明或许已经将时间机器
an advanced alien civilization might have a time machine...
在数千年前就已经打开了
that was switched on thousands 0f years ago.
我们也许可以利用他们的时间穿梭
We may be able to use their time travel...
回去拜访我们的祖先
to go back to visit our ancient past...
因为 如果他们拥有发达的时间旅行
because if they have developed time travel...
比如说 一万年前
let's say, 10,000 years ago...
还有会有同样的限制
it would still have the same limitation...
然而 我们一旦遇到他们 就可以用上它
but once we encounter them, we could use it...
或许有那么一天
and perhaps someday...
我们可以去参观古埃及和古罗马
we may be able to visit ancient Egypt and ancient Rome.
目前 马利特的重点
For now, Mallett is focused...
放在他的时间机器获准建造上
on getting his time machine built...
这个项目光启动费用就需要25万美元
a project that will require $250,000 in startup costs alone.
钱是敢于涉足时间穿梭的任何一位物理学家
Money is just one obstacle facing any physicist...
都面临的一个障碍
daring to dabble in time travel.
同时也存在着似是而非
There are also certain paradoxes...
许多人认为时间穿梭是不可能的
that many believe make time travel impossible...
比如臭名昭著的祖父悖论
like the infamous grandfather paradox.
设想一下 你回到过去 在你祖父遇上你祖母之前
lmagine you go back in time and kill your own grandfather...
将其杀死
before he meets your grandmother.
这样你就绝不可能再生出来了
Therefore, you never would've been born...
这样从一开始 也就不可能回到过去了
and therefore couldn't have gone back in time...in the first place.
于是 循环就成了
And then the loop is set up of...
可能 不可能
possible, impossible...
发生 不会发生
happened, it didn't happen.
但是马利特认为
But Mallett believes...
理论物理学的最新进展
recent advances in theoretical physics...
表明这些似是而非根本就不是什么问题
suggest that these paradoxes aren't a problem at all.
现在很多物理学家突发奇想认为
Many physicists now believe in the far-out notion...
我们的宇宙只是许多平行宇宙中的一个
that our universe...is just one of many parallel universes.
因此 当你回到过去时
So that when you go back in time...
你可能实际上是进入了一个平行宇宙
you might actually be entering a parallel universe...
在其中 你可以改变事件
in which you can alter events...
而不影响你来的那个宇宙
without affecting the universe you came from.
我们认为时间长河可能存在着漩涡
We believe that the river of time can have whirlpools...
你或许能够通过它回到过去
whirlpools by which you may be able to go back...
碰到你出生以前的父母
and meet your parents before you're born...
或者甚至分叉进入两条河里
or perhaps even fork into two rivers...
这样你就可以改变过去
by which you can actually alter the past...
创造一个备用的宇宙
to create an alternate universe.
这就是 如今现代物理学非常前卫的整个理论
These are all theories...that are at the very forefront of modern physics today.
马利特认为我们或许用不了一个世纪
Mallett believes we may be as little as a century away...
人类就可以进行时间穿梭了
from time travel by humans.
不过他回去救父亲为时已晚了
Still too late for him to travel back in time...to save his father.
- 怎么称呼？- 洛基
- And your name? - Rocky.
- 幸会 - 谢谢
- Nice to meet you. - Okay, thank you.
请记得空间发生的事情
Rememberwhat's happening to space.
它在不停地旋转
lt's swirling around.
然而他的个人损失已经为后人的新天地
But his personal loss has opened a door...
打开了一扇门
for a newworld forfuture generations.
我基于这个基本方程式上发展起来的
l developed the basic equations for this.
已经让我能够与世界分享某些东西
lt has led to my being able...to share something with the world...
那是我以前从不能分享到的
that l would never have been able to share before.
我感觉那其实是对我老爸能够做到的最好的缅怀
And l feel that,that it's actually...a fitting memorial to my father...that l've been able to do that.
对此我感觉良好
l feel very good about that.
对于宇宙最早的形成
As the universe was first forming...
科学家认为
scientists believe...
其成分不只是构成我们周围一切的常规物质
it was comprised of more thanjust the regular matter...that now makes up everything around us.
他们认为它具有几乎等量的反物质
They believe it had...an almost equal amount of anti-matter...
物质的难以捉摸的邪恶孪生兄弟
matter's elusive evil twin.
如果你回到宇宙的最初期
If you go back to the very early universe...
结果就是它是由物质和反物质构成的
it turns out that it was made of matter and anti-matter.
原来每个粒子都有一个反粒子
lt turns out that every particle has an anti-particle.
听上去好像很荒唐但却是真的
And it sounds kind of crazy, but it's real...
有点科幻 告诉你 反物质
and sort of sci-fi, you know, anti-matter.
然而 神秘的反物质究竟是什么
But what is this mysterious anti-matter...
又都到哪去了呢？
and where did all of it go?
反物质其实就像物质
Anti-matter is exactly like matter.
它的不同之处实际上在于
The difference between it is the fact...
它与之关联的电荷完全不同
that it has a completely different charge...associated with it.
常规物质的成分是原子
Regular matter is made of atoms...
接下来的成分是次原子粒子
which in turn are made of subatomic particles...
比如带负电荷的电子和带正电荷的质子
like negatively charged electrons...and positively charged protons.
反物质是这些粒子的对应面
Anti-matter are the opposite of these particles.
它们有相同的质量
They have the same mass...
却有着相反的电荷
but the opposite electrical charge.
质子是正电荷粒子 是原子核
Proton's a positively charged particle...that's the nucleus of the atom.
而反质子就是负电荷质子
The anti-proton would be a negatively charged proton...
具有相同的质量
that has exactly the same mass.
在我们的宇宙间 异性相吸
ln our universe, opposites attract...
粒子和反粒子相互吸引
and particles and anti-particles are pulled together.
有人会认为这种关系是天合之作
One would think this is...a relationship made for the heavens.
然而每次物质与反物质打交道时
But every time matter comes in contact with anti-matter...
结果无一例外
the outcome is the same...
它们同归于尽
they annihilate each other.
想象一下空中两架飞机迎面飞翔的情况
lmagine two spaceships hurtling through space...on a collision course.
一架是常规物质做成的
One is made of regular matter.
另一架是外星文明造的反物质飞船
The other is an anti-matter craft...built by an alien civilization.
碰撞将非常壮观
The impact would be spectacular...
将不会留下任何残骸
and there would be no wreckage left behind...
供宇宙撞机调查员来审视
for cosmic crash investigators to examine.
物质与反物质消失殆尽
The matter and the anti-matter disappear.
扑的一下 它们不见了
Poof, they're gone.
但是 能量没有消失
But the energy doesn't disappear.
能量以两种能量非常高的γ射线的形式再现:光子
The energy re-emerges in the form...of two very energetic gamma rays: photons.
锁定在很小质量里的能量相当惊人
And the amount of energy...locked up in a tiny amount of mass...is quite astonishing.
如果你将物质与反物质结合在一块 就会爆炸
lf you take matter and anti-matter...and combine it, it is explosive.
事实上 这是宇宙间最大的能源之一:
And in fact, it is one of the greatest sources...of energy in the universe...
物质与反物质的碰撞
the collision of matter and anti-matter.
所以我是你的话
So if l were you...
就不会将反物质放进口袋
l would not put anti-matter in your pocket...
如果你知道什么是值得的话
if you knowwhat's good for you.
反物质在碰上物质时极易挥发
Volatile as anti-matter is when it meets matter...
存在着巨大的潜能
there's a tremendous energy potential...
只要我们知道如何去驾驭它
ifwe knew how to harness it.
为了得到物质里究竟锁定了多少能量的概念
So to get an idea...how much energy is locked up in matter...
如果你能想上片刻
if you imagine for a minute...
这里有两堆沙子
that these two piles of sand are...
一堆是物质 另一堆是反物质
that one is matter and one is anti-matter...
你将它们放在一块
and you let them come together...
它们就会湮灭并产生能量
they would annihilate and produce energy.
会有多少能量呢？
How much energy?
供应整个加州一周的能量就在这两堆沙子里
Enough energy to power all of California for a week...just in those two piles of sand.
围绕反物质最大的谜团在于
The biggest mystery surrounding anti-matter is this...
如果在宇宙早期物质与反物质几乎是等量的话
if there were nearly equal amounts...of matter and anti-matter in the early universe...
那么现在所有的反物质都到哪里去了呢？
then where is all the anti-matter now?
宇宙最大的谜团之一
One of the great mysteries of the universe...
就是我们的邪恶孪生兄弟 反物质究竟怎么啦
is what happened to our evil twin, anti-matter.
我们扫视天堂的角角落落
Everywhere we look in the heavens...
只看到普通物质
we see ordinary matter.
没有见到反物质
We don't see anti-matter.
只有少量的反物质存在于银河系中心
There's only a small amount of anti-matter...coming out of the center of the Milky Way galaxy.
为何这个宇宙看上去全市由物质构成的
Why this universe appears to be made entirely of matter...
而没有见到什么反物质 真是一头雾水
and there isn't much anti-matter to be seen out there...
我不认为会一直解释不通
l don't think it'll ever be explained anyway...is a mystery.
但是 脑子里需要有个说法
but the mind hunts for an explanation.
一种可能或许就是
One possibility is that perhaps there was...
在宇宙早期物质的比例要稍高于反物质
a slightly higher percentage of matter than anti-matter...in the early universe.
因此 当粒子与反粒子在湮灭战里碰撞时
So as the particles and anti-particles collided...in a war of annihilation...
小部分物质幸存了下来
that small percentage of matter survived...
成为了最古老战场上幸存的老兵
the last living veterans of our most ancient battlefield.
相对10亿个反质子
For every billion anti-protons...
你就需要有十亿零一个质子
you need a billion and one protons.
一旦10亿个都牺牲了
Then the billion all annihilate...
你就留下了那一个质子
and you're left with that one proton.
剩余的是我方
And the leftover is us.
我们都是剩余财产
We are the residue.
我们都是在物质与反物质碰撞那个瞬间
We are the leftover of this titanic blast of energy...
释放出来的巨大能量爆发的残余
released by the collision of matter and anti-matter...at the instant of time.
我们最先进的理论尚无法解释
Our most advanced theories cannot explain...
为何物质与反物质之间存在着这种不平衡
why there was this asymmetry between matter and anti-matter.
但是 苍天有眼 它存在了
But thank God it exists.
否则 我们将不会存在
Otherwise, we wouldn't be here.
不过即使物质胜出
But even though matter prevailed...
构成了我们周遭的万物
to make up everything we see around us...
但是有没有在遥远的星系或空间
could there be distant galaxies or regions of space...
存在着反物质称霸一方的可能性呢？
where anti-matter still reigns supreme?
有可能会有整个星系
lt may be that there are entire galaxies...
就是由99.9%的反物质构成
that are just 99.9 percent anti-matter...
就像我们物质构成的星系一样
just like this one is matter.
如果一个反物质星系撞进物质星系
And if an anti-matter galaxy...were to run into a matter galaxy...
那么它们双双会毁于巨大的闪光和能量中
then they both would be annihilated...in some stupendous flash of light and power.
奇怪的是 科学家已经知道了如何
As strange as it is...scientists have learned how to create...
在实验室加速器里创造微量的医用反物质
minute quantities of anti-matter...in laboratory accelerators for medical purposes.
来自衰变的放射物质的反物质粒子
Particles of anti-matter...from decaying radioactive material...
被注射进人体 进行大脑正电子发射断层扫描(PET 扫描)
are injected into the body...to create PET scans of the brain.
许多人没有意识到
Many people don't realize...
在他们去医院进行PET扫描时
that when they go to the hospital...and have a PET scan...
自己实际上被注射了反物质
they're actually being injected...with a source of anti-matter.
PET中的P代表正电子
The P in PET corresponds to positrons.
正电子就是反电子
Positrons are anti-electrons.
一旦它进入到我们想了解的人体某个部位
And when...and it goes to some part of the body...that we're trying to figure out what's going on...
接下来正电子会被释放出来
then when the positron's emitted...
它会很快找上电子
it finds an electron very quickly...
一起湮灭
annihilates with it...
就会有γ射线从体内发出
and the gamma rays come out of the body...
从而被侦察到
and are detected.
它集中在脑力活跃的部分大脑
lt concentrates in the parts of the brain...where there's mental activity...
于是我们可以检测出正电子辐射
and then we can detect the emission...of positron radiation.
这就让脑部扫描
So this allows brain scans...
给我们大脑思考的漂亮图像
to give us gorgeous photographs of the thinking brain...
其可能性全靠反物质
made possible by anti-matter.
在反物质帮助解开了人脑秘密的同时
While anti-matter has helped to unlock...the secrets of the human brain...
人脑尚无法解开反物质的全部之谜
the human brain has yet to unlock...all the secrets of anti-matter.
我们确实不知道为何现在的宇宙是物质构成的
We do not knowwhy...the universe is made of matter now...
但是 我们正朝着解决这个问题迈进
but we are making progress towards answering that question.
要知道 在小步快跑
You know, little steps at a time.
如同我们永恒变化的宇宙中的许多秘密一样
Like many mysteries in our ever-changing universe...
反物质的真相或许目前仍然属于未解之谜
the truth about anti-matter may remain for now...in the realm of the unexplained.
火星与神秘始终如影相随
Mars and mystery have always gone hand in hand.
然而 这颗红色行星最有趣的秘密
But the most intriguing mystery of the red planet...
就在于与外来入侵者毫不相干
has nothing to do with alien invaders.
科学证据表明火星曾是颗极像地球的行星
Scientific evidence suggests that Mars...was once a more Earth-like planet...
具有维系生命的一个关键元素 水
with one of the key elements to support life...water.
水曾大量存在于火星
Water existed in abundance on Mars.
我们发现了古河流的证据
We find the evidence of old flows.
我们在其大气层里发现了零星的水蒸汽
We see a little tiny bit 0f water vapor...in the atmosphere.
火星上甚至还存在古河谷和冲积平原模样的特征
There are even features on Mars...that look like old rivervalleys and flood plains.
它曾是颗具有海洋的热带行星
lt was once a tropical planet with oceans and seas...
但是已经是山穷水尽
but all that water disappeared.
火星上的水怎么会通通消失殆尽的呢？
How could all the water on Mars have simply vanished?
为何会不见的呢？
And why did it disappear?
这些都是科学家孜孜以求之谜
These are mysteries...that scientists are struggling to solve.
火星漫游者和轨道器收集到的地质证据
Geologic evidence gathered by the Mars rovers and orbiters...
揭示了在35亿年前
suggest that 3.5 billion years ago...
火星潮湿地表发生了戏剧性改变了
Mars' watery surface changed dramatically.
过去温润的行星变成了干冷之地
The once-temperate planet became a cold, dry place...
水消失了
and the watervanished.
不过弄清楚了水消失的时间
But figuring out when the water disappeared...
并不会告诉你水去了哪里以及原因
doesn't tell you where it went orwhy.
火星上的水消失了很久很久了
The water on Mars was lost...a very, very, very long time ago...
我说是由几十亿年了
and l'm talking billions 0f years.
能让你了解水去了何处的线索早不存在了
And the clues that would lead you to know...where that waterwent are long gone.
火星上一系列事件
A series of events on Mars...
显示出已经剧烈地改变了那里的水景
appears to have drastically changed the watery landscape.
火星经受了剧烈的火山活动时期
Mars endured an intense period ofvolcanism...
喷发的熔岩覆盖了地表
that spewed lava across the surface.
在其尘埃落定时
When it finally ended...
行星的熔融铁核凝固了
the planet's molten iron core solidified.
这有可能造成了火星
This may have been what caused Mars...
失去了自己的磁场和臭氧保护层
to lose its magnetic field and protective ozone layer.
这就留下了脆弱的大气层
This left the atmosphere vulnerable...
来面对非常强烈的太阳风
to the solarwind from our Sun...which is quite powerful.
太阳风摧残了火星数百万年
Solarwinds pummeled the planet for millions 0f years...
剥走了所有残留的大气层
stripping any remaining atmosphere.
过去变作雨雪的水蒸气
Nowwatervapor that once fell as snow or rain...
已经挣脱了火星微弱的引力场
escaped the planet's small gravitational field.
水蒸发到大气层里变成了水蒸气
The water is brought up into the atmosphere...as watervapor...
遭遇到紫外线辐射的轰击
and it's bombarded by ultraviolet radiation...
会把水 也就是H2O分解成氢和氧
which can split water, which is H2O...
氢是众所周知最轻的气体
And the hydrogen, being the lightest gas known...into hydrogen and oxygen.
上升到大气层的顶部
floats up to the top of the atmosphere...
会被太阳风刮走
and can get swept away by the solarwinds.
关于火星水消失的另一个理论
Another theory for the loss of Mars' water...
涉及到外来的威胁
involves a threat from outside the planet.
有证据表明在太阳系早期
There's evidence that in the early years...of the solar system...
火星置身致命的路径上
Mars resided in a deadly flight path.
约39亿年前 有一个星团
There's one cluster, about 3.9 billion years ago...
叫做大轰击
called the great bombardment...
必定是连续撞击那颗行星
that really must have peppered that planet...with many, many impacts.
那种事件实际上会将物质和大气抛离星球
And that kind of an event...would have actually thrown material and atmosphere...right off of the planet...
抛离引力场
and outside of the gravitational field.
我们来想象一下 这里有颗小行星
Let's imagine that we have an asteroid here...
这颗小行星其实大小如一座山
and this asteroid is really the size of a mountain.
可以想象它以很快的速度从空中滚落
And imagine this is tumbling through space...at very high speed...
时速达到数万英里
and we're talking tens of thousands of miles per hour.
如果我们看到它从天而降
lfwe come zipping in at high speed...
啪哒
splat.
它飞到了空中
lt's lost to space.
大部分被消失了
Much of it will sink in.
部分会成为大气散布进太空
Some will become atmospheric gases...sputtered away to space.
部分会消失
Some will be lost.
关于火星水消失之谜的其它答案
Other answers to the mystery of Mars' disappearing water...
有可能深藏在红色星球的深处
may be hidden deep inside the red planet.
部分水会和二氧化碳结合
Some of the water combined with carbon dioxide...
形成极地冰盖 厚达两英里
to form polar ice caps up to two miles deep...
覆盖其大部分地表的冻土
and a permafrost that covers much of the surface.
然而 有证据表明 在冰层下面
But there's evidence that beneath the ice...
依然存在着液态水
liquid water still flows.
火星上大量的水进入了地下
Much of the water on Mars has gone underground...
其中部分肯定进入到了深处
and some of it certainly has migrated...
在那里有足够的温度
down to a depth where it's warm enough...
使其保存为液态水
for it to exist as liquid water.
而且一旦温度降低
Then when it gets colder...
就会冻成冰冻层 也就是说
it's gonna be frozen into a cryosphere, if you like...
地下的冰
an ice part of the subsurface.
而靠近地表 就会干涸
Then near the surface, it's gonna dry out...
水就会透过地表进入大气层
as the water can move through the soil...and go into the atmosphere.
亚利桑那大学的科学家彼得·史密斯
University ofArizona scientist Peter Smith...
渴望解开火星水消失之谜
is eager to solve the mystery of Mars' disappearing water.
我在这里挖条小沟
Okay, l'm digging a little trench here...
让你看看结果
to showyou what happens...
如果你挖开极度干旱的地表
if you get below the absolute hyper-arid surface...
往下一两英尺
and go downjust a foot or so...
因为 这里类似于我们在火星上要做的事情
because this is similar...to what we're gonna be doing on Mars.
史密斯是航天局凤凰号火星任务的主要研究员
Smith is the principle investigator...for Nasa's Phoenix Mars mission.
这个机器人探测器只有一个目的
lt's a robotic probe with one simple objective...
就是登陆火星找水
land on Mars and follow the water.
那里的水怎么回事？
What happened to that water?
它可能会冻成地下冰
lt could have frozen into underground ice...
乃至液态水的蓄水层
or even aquifers of liquid water.
那就是我们现在要搜寻的
These are something we're looking for today...
利用无线电和雷达
using radio and radar...
穿透地表 努力找出这些水源
to penetrate through the surface and try and locate...these reservoirs of water.
史密斯认为亚利桑那州的威尔科克斯干盐湖
Smith believes thatArizona's Wilcox Playa...
能够反映凤凰号最终挖开火星地表后
reflects what scientists will find...
科学家将会发现的情况
when Phoenix finally scratches the red Martian surface.
即使其地表炎热 干燥 高盐
Even though the surface is parched and salty and dry...
但是 到了地下6英寸
just within six inches of the surface...
就是很湿润的泥土 像个蓄水池
is a very wet clay like a reservoir 0f water...
是这些潮湿土壤和这些泥土里的生命的
and there's a whole ecosystem of life...that's living in these wet soils...
整个生态系统
and these clays.
下雨时 会冒出地面
When it rains, it comes to the surface.
事实上 你可以看到小水潭
And, in fact, you see little pools...
还可以看到一些小东西
where actually brine shrimp...
那是困在这些泥土里的
that are locked into these soils.
我们想知道在火星的适当地方的地下
We wonder ifwe get down under the surface...at the right place on Mars...
就是在冻土地带
and that is the permafrost region...
能否看到这种生态系统
can we find the same sort of ecosystem...
整个冰层是否会随气候变化而融化？
around the ice...melting over time as climate changes?
有可能适合某种火星生命的生存
lt's habitable for some sort of Martian life forms.
有些人认为地球生命来自火星
Some believe that life on Earth...originated on Mars...
其奇怪的变迁预示了我们的命运
and that its strange transformation...foretells our destiny.
果真如此 寻找火星上的水
lf that's true, finding Mars' water...
就有可能引导我们回到宇宙的起源
may lead us back to our cosmic beginnings...
以及走向未来
and into the future.
提起宇宙
When it comes to the universe...
我们的认识仅限于我们已经了解的
what we know is surpassed only by what we have yet to learn.
在所有的未解之谜中
And of all the unexplained mysteries...
有一个是最大的
one remains the greatest of all.
大爆炸之前是个什么情况
Did anything come before the Big Bang...
抑或那个事件真是一切的开端？
orwas that event truly the beginning of everything?
果真如此 那又是什么点燃了爆炸呢？
And if it was, what was the spark that lit it?
这就是整个科学中最大的谜团
This is the greatest mystery in all of science.
是什么启动了创世本身的呢？
What started creation itself?
大爆炸理论里头存在着这个巨大的漏洞
Big bang theory has this tremendous hole in it.
我们茫然不知
We are clueless.
我们茫然不知于是什么将大爆炸付之行动的
We are clueless as to what set the Big Bang into motion.
大爆炸是关于137亿年前宇宙诞生的宇宙论模型
The Big Bang is the cosmological model...for the birth of our universe, 13.7 billion years ago.
宇宙中的一切
Everything in our universe...
都可以追溯到那一刻
can be traced back to that moment.
起始那一刻似乎存在着这个神秘点
There seems to be...this mysterious point at the beginning...
我们将其称之为奇点
and we call it the singularity.
即使它很神秘
But even though it's mysterious...
还有很多未解之谜牵涉其中
and has many open questions associated with it...
但它仍不失为我们时间表上的良好开端
it still makes a good starting point...for our timeline.
但是 我们的科学仪器
But our scientific instruments are blind and deaf...
对大爆炸以前时期一无所知
to the period before the Big Bang...
果真存在过这个时期的话
if such a period existed at all.
奇点就像是我们永远无法逾越的界限
The singularity is like...a horizon that we can never see beyond.
因为在创世中
Because in the creation...
时间是伴随空间 物质一起创造出来的
time was created along with space...and along with matter...
大爆炸就是那种事件
and the Big Bang is just that sort of event.
因此 是不可能知道创世之前的情况的
And therefore, it's impossible to knowwhat happened...before the creation event.
不过 对大爆炸之前情况的揣摩
Nevertheless, scientific speculation...as to what happened before the Big Bang...
重要的是激发了天文物理学最伟大的思想
is something that intrigues...the greatest minds in astrophysics.
有些理论家认为我们的宇宙
Some theorists believe that our universe...
会定期经历一次大爆炸
experiences Big Bangs at regular intervals.
这个循环模型认为每万亿年
This cyclic model proposes that every trillion years...
就会有一次大爆炸 随后宇宙开始膨胀
there's a Big Bang afterwhich the universe expands...
接着又坍缩
before again collapsing...
为下一次大爆炸创造条件
setting the stage for another Big Bang.
有些有趣的方法可以
There's interesting ways that can connect...
联系上前一个宇宙的故事
with the story of a previous universe.
我们宇宙的结尾可以带来另一个宇宙的开端
The end of one universe can bring the beginning of another.
也许从来没有过开端
Maybe there neverwas a start...
它或许是从更早的时刻一直延续着
that it's somehow been ongoing from an earlier moment...
根本就没有过什么创世者
and never had a creator at all.
不过我们对大爆炸之前的解释有可能
But we might be closer to an explanation...
超过了我们的了解
of the pre-Big Bang than we know.
依然回荡在宇宙间的大爆炸产生的宇宙回响
The cosmic reverberations from the Big Bang...that still echo through the universe...
实际上 或许掌握着奇点之前那一刻的答案
may actually hold the answer...to the moment before the singularity.
原来这些驻波是我们了解当今宇宙的关键
lt turns out these standing waves...are key to how we understand the universe today.
在一开始 膨胀就给了宇宙一个巨大的冲击
lnflation gives the universe...one big hit at the beginning...
就像我在这里打击面前的这个罐子
just like l'm hitting the pot right here.
它产生了驻波
lt forms the standing waves...
我们可以在现在的宇宙辐射中
and we can look for those symmetrical patterns...
看到这些对称的图案
in the cosmic radiation today.
所以 我们发送卫星 观察辐射
So we send our satellites out, we observe the radiation...
观察对称的驻波
the symmetrical standing waves.
新一波探测器 重力波探测器
A newwave of detectors, gravity wave detectors...
将在下一个十年送往外太空
will be launched into outer space...in the next decade.
通过激光相连
Connected by laser beams...
创世产生的任何冲击波都会震荡这些激光束
any shockwave from the incident of creation...will jiggle these laser beams...
这样我们就能够记录到
and we'll be able to then record...
大爆炸本身所留下的震动
the vibrations left over from the Big Bang itself.
这就是我坚信我们在未来几十年里能够
That's why l'm confident that we'll be able...
不光探测到大爆炸本身
to probe notjust the Big Bang itself...
甚至还有大爆炸前期的原因所在
but even the pre-Big Bang era in the coming decades.
激光还将探测到
The lasers will also detect...
膨胀能量的源头
sources of inflationary energy...
甚至还能确定创造大爆炸的机制
and perhaps determine the mechanism...that created the Big Bang.
如果我们努力解决了这个最大的谜团
If we struggle to solve the greatest mystery of all...
那么我们对真正了解宇宙怎么能不抱希望呢？
how can we ever hope to really understand the universe?
每当你解决了一个问题
Wheneveryou get an answer to a question...
总会引出更多的问题
it almost always leads to more questions.
你取得了进展 谜团得以解决
You make progress and mysteries can get solved...
但另一方面总是会有更多的谜团
but then there'll always be more mysteries.
我们是宇宙不断尝试了解自我的产物
We are the result...of the universe attempting to understand itself.
那就是 我对我们在宇宙中的定位的观点
That's my conception of our place in the universe.
因此 这让人很难理解
And so that makes it difficult to understand...
尽管如此 还是极有可能的
but nevertheless, it might be possible.
宇宙在不断变化之中
The universe is constantly changing.
但是规律 物理定律是一成不变的
But the laws, the laws of physics...are immutable.
它们不会改变
They don't change...
它给了我们摆脱混乱的希望
and that gives us hope that out of all this chaos...
我们将能够解释
we'll be able to explain...
它是如何从一开始一路走来的
how it all got here to begin with.
在我们永恒变化的宇宙中
ln our ever-changing universe...
未解之谜会继续困惑我们
the unexplained mysteries will continue to elude us.
但是我们正逼近解开我们的终极之谜
But we are edging ever closer...to unlocking the ultimate secrets...
承前启后 继往开来
the keys to our past and the pathways to ourfuture.
虽然 科学已经搞明白了很多东西
While science has made sense of many things...
但是 还有大量有待认识的东西
there is still plenty left to be discovered...
深藏在广袤 幽深 神秘的宇宙间
about our vast, dark, and mysterious universe.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing